<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 UNINETT

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option)
any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple
Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.

$Id$
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Configuration - Web Module</title>
        <author email="cato.olsen@uninett.no">Cato Olsen</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Web Module">
            <p>
            The Web Module's configuration contains settings (such as language
            and cookie information) used by the various servlets that represents
            Moria. The most important servlets are the login and logout
            servlets, the Axis servlet (which handles the SOAP interface of
            Moria) and a few utility type servlets, such as the information
            servlet.
            </p>
            <p>
            It is important that there exist a language bundle for the default
            language; otherwise the the login and logout servlet will fail
            whenever they try to use this default language.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Core Properties">
                <p>
                The core properties required for Moria are as follows:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.login.url_prefix</code>
                    <p>
                    The URL of the login servlet itself. The example file below
                    assumes Moria is deployed locally.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.lang_common</code>
                    <p>
                    A comma-separated list of abbreviations and HTML display
                    names for available languages. The list elements themselves
                    consists of a two-character language code (consistency is
                    required throughout the various configuration files, such as
                    the
                    <a href="config_authorization_manager.html#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    file), a colon, and the HTML display name. The example file
                    below configures Norwegian (bokmål) and English.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.org_<i>XX</i></code>
                    <p>
                    These properties contain a comma-separated list of
                    organization names to display when using the language with
                    two-character code <i>XX</i>. The list elements themselves
                    consist of a unique organization name (consistency is
                    required throughout the various configuration files, such as
                    the
                    <a href="config_authorization_manager.html#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    file), a colon, and the HTML display name. The example file
                    below configures Norwegian (bokmål) and English for one
                    imaginary organization.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.login.ticket_param</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the URL parameter containing the Moria ticket
                    ID.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to disallow SSO, if so chosen by
                    the user.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.ttl</code>
                    <p>
                    The time to live, in hours, for the cookie used to disallow
                    SSO.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to carry SSO ticket ID.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.ttl</code>
                    <p>
                    The time to live, in hours, for the cookie used to carry SSO
                    ticket ID.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.lang.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to store the user's preferred
                    language.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.login.default_language</code>
                    <p>
                    The default Moria language, which should match one of the 
                    two-letter language abbreviations already defined. The
                    example file below will use English.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to store a user's previously
                    selected organization.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.ttl</code>
                    <p>
                    The time to live, in hours, for the cookie used to store the 
                    user's previously selected organization.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.faqlink</code>
                    <p>
                    The URL to the FAQ document.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.faq.status</code>
                    <p>
                    Link to the Moria2 Status servlet (used in the FAQ
                    document).
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.faq.owner</code>
                    <p>
                    Organization name of the Moria2 owner; that is, the
                    organization responsible for the Moria2 service (used in the
                    FAQ document). <em>This property is optional; if not set,
                    a text similar to "the Moria organization" will be used
                    instead.</em>
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.resource.date</code>
                    <p>
                    A date for when the web pages were last updates/Moria2 was
                    last deployed. <em>This property is optional; if not set, a
                    null value will be used instead.</em>
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.resource.link</code>
                    <p>
                    A link to the home page of the Moria2 owner's organization.
                    <em>This property is optional; if not set, a null value will
                    be used instead.</em>
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>#no.feide.moria.web.resource.mail</code>
                    <p>
                    A mail contact address shown on the web pages of Moria.
                    <em>This property is optional; if not set, a null value will
                    be used instead.</em>
                    </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Information Servlet Properties">
                <p>
                The following required properties are used by the information
                servlet:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.information.feideattribs_xml</code>
                    <p>
                    Gives the path and name of the file containing the actual
                    attribute descriptions. The XML file contains a root element
                    <i>AttributeFile</i> with one or more <i>Attribute</i> child
                    elements. Each <i>Attribute</i> element must contain the
                    child elements <i>Key</i> (which has a text child element
                    giving the physical attribute name), <i>ResourceBundle</i>
                    (which has a text child element providing the localized
                    description text for the attribute), <i>Relevance</i> (which
                    has a text child element that is either
                    <code>Mandatory</code> or <code>Optional</code>), and
                    <i>Link</i> (which has a text child element that gives the
                    URL of this attribute to a web page describing the
                    attribute).
                    </p> 
                    <p>
                    Example attribute description file:
                    </p>
                    <source>
&lt;?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

&lt;attributefile>

    &lt;attribute&gt; 
        &lt;key&gt;mail&lt;/key&gt;
        &lt;resourcebundle&gt;rb_mail&lt;/resourcebundle&gt;
        &lt;relevance&gt;Mandatory&lt;/relevance&gt;
        &lt;link&gt;http://www.feide.no/dokumenter/feide-schema-current.html#mail&lt;/link&gt;
    &lt;/attribute>&gt;

&lt;/attributefile>
                    </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.information.url_prefix</code>
                    <p>
                    Should give the URL used to access to the information
                    servlet.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Status Servlet Property">
            <p>
                The following property are used by the status servlet:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.backendstatus.status_xml</code>
                    <p>Gives the path and name of the file containing the information
                    about the test-users. The XML file contains a rootelement <i>Testuserlist</i>
                    with one or more <i>User</i> child elements. Each <i>User</i> element must
                    contain the child elements <i>Name</i> (which has a text child element
                    giving the name of a test-user) and <i>Password</i> (which has a text child
                    element giving the password of a test-user).
                    </p>
                    <p>Example of a status.xml file</p>
                    <source>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?&gt;

&lt;Testuserlist&gt;

   &lt;User&gt;
      &lt;Name&gt;test@test.no&lt;/Name&gt;
      &lt;Password&gt;test&lt;/Password&gt;
   &lt;/User&gt;

&lt;/Testuserlist&gt;
			</source>
			</li>
		</ul>
        <p>     
        Example Web Module configuration file:
        </p>
        <source>
#
# Configuration properties for Moria itself:
#

# The URL of the login servlet.
no.feide.moria.web.login.url_prefix=http://localhost:8080/moria/Login

# The name of the parameter used to contain the redirect URL when logging out.
no.feide.moria.web.logout.url_param=redirUrl

# Abbreviations and display names for available languages.
no.feide.moria.web.lang_common=nb:Bokm&amp;aring;l,en:English

# Organization names when using the language EN.
no.feide.moria.web.org_en=my.org:My Organization

# Organization names when using the language NB.
no.feide.moria.web.org_nb=my.org:Min organisasjon

# Name of URL parameter containing the Moria ticket ID.
no.feide.moria.web.login.ticket_param=moriaID

# Name of cookie used to disallow SSO.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.name=MoriaDenySSOCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookie used to disallow SSO.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.ttl=1

# Name of cookie used to carry SSO ticket ID.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.name=MoriaSSOCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookie used to carry SSO ticket ID.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.ttl=1

# Name of cookie used to store user's preferred language.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.lang.name=MoriaUserLanguageCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookies used to store user's preferred language.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.lang.ttl=1

# Default Moria language.
no.feide.moria.web.login.default_language=en

# Name of cookie used to store user's previously selected organization.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.name=MoriaUserOrganizationCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookies used to store user's previously selected organization.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.ttl=1

# Link to the Moria2 FAQ.
no.feide.moria.web.faqlink=http://localhost:8080/moria/faq

# Link to the Moria2 Status servlet (used in the FAQ).
no.feide.moria.web.faq.status=http://localhost:8080/moria/Status

# Organization name of the Moria2 owner (used in the FAQ).
no.feide.moria.web.faq.owner=My Moria Organization

# Web pages last-updated date.
no.feide.moria.web.resource.date=2005-03-29

# Link to the Moria2 owner's web pages.
no.feide.moria.web.resource.link=http://www.some.org

# Mail address shown on the web pages.
#no.feide.moria.web.resource.mail=info@some.org

#
# Configuration properties relevant for the information service (InformationServlet):
#

# Giving the URL to the information servlet.
no.feide.moria.web.information.url_prefix=http://localhost:8080/moria/Information

# Configuration property for the attribute description file name.
no.feide.moria.web.information.feideattribs_xml=/some/path/attribs.xml

#
# Configuration property relevant for the status service (StatusServlet):
#

# Configuration proprety for the status.xml file.
no.feide.moria.web.backendstatus.status_xml=/some/path/status.xml
		        </source>
		    </subsection>
		    <subsection name="Static Content">
		    <p>
		    In addition to the configuration settings mentioned above, the
		    following static resources are used by Moria2. All URLs assume that
		    Moria2 has been deployed to <tt>http://localhost:8080/moria</tt>;
		    check your servlet container's documentation for details on how to
		    accomplish this - <a href="http://www.caucho.com/">Resin</a>, for
		    example, will let you put these files in
		    <tt>RESIN_HOME/doc/resource</tt>.
		    </p>
		    <ul>
		    	<li>
		    	<code>stil.css</code>
		    	<p>
		    	A stylesheet file, used in formatting the browser output.
		    	<a href="resource/stil.css">Example</a>.<br/>
                URL: <tt>http://localhost:8080/moria/resource/stil.css</tt>
                </p>
		    	</li>
		    	<li>
		    	<code>emblem-topp.gif</code>
		    	<p>
		    	A logo image, displayed on top right of the web pages.
		    	<a href="resource/emblem-topp.gif">Example</a>.<br/>
		    	URL: <tt>http://localhost:8080/moria/resource/emblem-topp.gif</tt>
		    	</p>
		    	</li>
		    	<li>
		    	<code>logo.gif</code>
		    	<p>
				Another logo image, displayed on the top left of the web pages.
				<a href="resource/logo.gif">Example</a>.<br/>
		    	URL: <tt>http://localhost:8080/moria/resource/logo.gif</tt>
				</p>
		    	</li>
		    </ul>
		    </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
