<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 UNINETT

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option)
any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple
Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.

$Id$
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Configuration - Authorization Manager</title>
        <author email="cato.olsen@uninett.no">Cato Olsen</author>
    </properties>
    <body> 
        <section name="Authorization Manager">
            <p>
            The Authorization Manager is configured by an XML file which
            contains a <i>ClientAuthorizationConfig</i> element, which in turn
            contains a <i>Client</i> element for every client service allowed to
            use Moria.
            </p>
            <p>
            The actual service authentication is performed outside of Moria (by
            the application server) so password and/or certificates must be
            configured in the server that performs the authentication (for
            example, <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache</a> or
            <a href="http://www.caucho.com/">Resin</a>).
            </p>
            <!--
            TODO: NEED AN UPDATE! 
            <p><a href="authorization.dtd">DTD for the authorization configuration file</a>.</p>
            -->
            <p>
            A <i>Client</i> element consists of the following:
            <ol>
                <li>
                A required <i>name</i> attribute which is identical to the
                principal used for the client service's external authentication.
                </li>
                <li>
                A <i>DisplayName</i> child element with a text child element
                containing the full name of the client service. This is the
                service name that is presented on the login page.
                </li>
                <li>
                An <i>URL</i> child element with a text child element containing
                an URL pointing to the main page of the client service. This URL
                is used to connect a link from the displayed client service name
                (on the login page) to a page where the client service may
                describe itself to the user.                
                </li>
                <li>
                A <i>Home</i> child element with a text child element that
                specifies which organization the client service belongs to. The
                short-form organization names should be consistent with
                short-form organization names appearing elsewhere in other
                configuration files, such as the <a href="config_web_module.html#Web Module">Web
                Module</a> configuration file.
                <b><i>Not currently used.</i></b>
                <!--
                TODO: Is this actually not used?
                -->
                </li>
                <li>
                A <i>Language</i> child element with a text child element that
                gives the default language used on the web interfaces (such as
                the login web page) for this client service. This language will
                be used as the default language for the login page if the user
                has not previously selected another language. If not present the
                system-wide Moria default language will be used instead. Note
                that this two-character language code must match one of the
                two-character language codes defined in the
                <a href="config_web_module.html#Web Module">Web Module</a> configuration file.
                </li>
                <li>
                An <i>Affiliation</i> child element containing one or more
                <i>Organization</i> child elements, which again contain a text
                child element. The text child element should match the
                short-form organization names defined in the
                <a href="config_web_module.html#Web Module">Web Module</a> configuration file. Users
                belonging to one of these affiliated organizations may be
                authenticated against a secondary (or tertiary, and so on)
                authentication server (or location within the same
                authentication server) when using this service. This allows an
                organization to publish a service for which only a certain set
                of users may be authenticated without allowing these users to
                access other services (unless their organization is also
                affiliated with these services, of course).
                <!--
                TODO: Remember to update this description as the intended functionality is added.
                -->
                </li>
                <li>
                An <i>OrgsAllowed</i> child element containing one or more
                <i>Organization</i> child elements, which again contain a text
                child element. The text child element should match the
                short-form organization names defined in the
                <a href="config_web_module.html#Web Module">Web Module</a> configuration file. Users
                belonging to one of these allowed organizations may access this
                client service; others cannot.
                </li>
                <li>
                An <i>Attributes</i> child element containing one or more
                <i>Attribute</i> child elements. The <i>Attribute</i> child
                element(s) contain the attributes <i>name</i> (gives the
                physical name of a physical user attribute the client service is
                allowed to read), <i>sso</i> (true or false; tells whether the
                client service is allowed to read this attribute when using
                SSO), and <i>secLevel</i> (used to classify an attribute request
                according to security level and optionally display a
                warning/description to the user on the login page). Security
                levels range from 0 to 2, with 0 being the lowest. Note that
                for a client service to be allowed a ticket granting ticket the
                configuration must be allowed to read the <i>tgt</i> attribute
                and use it for SSO.
                </li>
                <li>
                The <i>Operations</i> child element contains one or more
                <i>Operation</i> child elements for those operations the client
                service is allowed to perform. The <i>Operation</i> child
                element has an attribute <i>name</i> specifying the allowed
                operation's name. The following operations are defined:
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Operation</th>
                        <th>Explanation</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><i>InteractiveAuth</i></td>
                        <td>Allow normal interactive authentication.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><i>DirectAuth</i></td>
                        <td>Allow the user's username/password to be sent
                            through the client service. Handle with care, as
                            this is a potential security pitfall.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><i>ProxyAuth</i></td>
                        <td>
                            Allows a subsystem to perform user authentication
                            using a proxy ticket. Also needed for the parent
                            system in order to be able to issue a proxy ticket.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><i>VerifyUserExistence</i></td>
                        <td>Allows the client service to check whether a given
                            user actually exists.</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                </li>
                <li>
                The <i>Subsystems</i> child element contains a
                <i>Subsystem</i> child element for every secondary client
                service the primary client service is allowed to use proxy
                authentication in cooperation with (that is, which secondary
                client service(s) are allowed to make use of proxy tickets
                issued to the primary client service). Each
                secondary client service must be configured to be allowed to use
                the operation <i>ProxyAuth</i>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            </p>
            <p>
            Example Authorization Manager configuration file:
            </p>
            <source>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?&gt;
&lt;ClientAuthorizationConfig&gt;
    &lt;Client name="test"&gt;
        &lt;DisplayName&gt;Foobar&lt;/DisplayName&gt;
        &lt;URL&gt;http://www.feide.no/&lt;/URL&gt;
        &lt;Home&gt;uio.no&lt;/Home&gt;
        &lt;Language&gt;no&lt;/Language&gt;
        &lt;Affiliation&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uninett.no"/&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uio.no"/&gt;
        &lt;/Affiliation&gt;
        &lt;OrgsAllowed&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uninett.no"/&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uio.no"/&gt;
       &lt;/OrgsAllowed&gt;        
        &lt;Attributes&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="attr1" sso="true" secLevel="0"/&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="attr2" sso="true" secLevel="1"/&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="attr3" sso="false" secLevel="2"/&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="tgt"   sso="true" secLevel="0"/&gt;
        &lt;/Attributes&gt;
        &lt;Operations&gt;
            &lt;Operation name="DirectAuth"/&gt;
            &lt;Operation name="InteractiveAuth"/&gt;
            &lt;Operation name="VerifyUserExistence"/&gt;
            &lt;Operation name="ProxyAuth"/&gt;
        &lt;/Operations&gt;
        &lt;Subsystems&gt;
            &lt;Subsystem name="sub1"/&gt;
            &lt;Subsystem name="sub2"/&gt;
        &lt;/Subsystems&gt;
    &lt;/Client&gt;
    
    &lt;Client name="sub1"&gt;
        &lt;DisplayName&gt;Subsystem 1&lt;/DisplayName&gt;
        &lt;URL&gt;http://www.feide.no/&lt;/URL&gt;
        &lt;Home&gt;uio.no&lt;/Home&gt;
        &lt;Language&gt;no&lt;/Language&gt;
        &lt;Affiliation&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uninett.no"/&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uio.no"/&gt;
        &lt;/Affiliation&gt;
        &lt;OrgsAllowed&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uninett.no"/&gt;
            &lt;Organization name="uio.no"/&gt;
        &lt;/OrgsAllowed&gt;
        &lt;Attributes&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="attr1" sso="true" secLevel="0"/&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="attr2" sso="true" secLevel="1"/&gt;
            &lt;Attribute name="attr3" sso="false" secLevel="2"/&gt;
        &lt;/Attributes&gt;
        &lt;Operations&gt;
            &lt;Operation name="ProxyAuth"/&gt;
        &lt;/Operations&gt;
        &lt;Subsystems&gt;
        &lt;/Subsystems&gt;
    &lt;/Client&gt;
&lt;/ClientAuthorizationConfig&gt;
            </source>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
