<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 UNINETT

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option)
any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple
Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.

$Id$
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Configuration - Web Module</title>
        <author email="cato.olsen@uninett.no">Cato Olsen</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Web Module">
            <p>
            The Web Module's configuration contains settings (such as language
            and cookie information) used by the various servlets that represents
            Moria. The most important servlets are the login and logout
            servlets, the Axis servlet (which handles the SOAP interface of
            Moria) and a few utility type servlets, such as the demo servlet and
            the information servlet.
            </p>
            <p>
            It is important that there exist a language bundle for the default
            language; otherwise the the login and logout servlet will fail
            whenever they try to use this default language.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Core Properties">
                <p>
                The core properties required for Moria are as follows:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.login.url_prefix</code>
                    <p>
                    The URL of the login servlet itself. The example file below
                    assumes Moria is deployed locally.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.logout.url_param</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the parameter used to contain the redirect URL
                    when logging out.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.lang_common</code>
                    <p>
                    A comma-separated list of abbreviations and HTML display
                    names for available languages. The list elements themselves
                    consists of a two-character language code (consistency is
                    required throughout the various configuration files, such as
                    the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    file), a colon, and the HTML display name. The example file
                    below configures Norwegian (bokmål) and English.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.org_<i>XX</i></code>
                    <p>
                    These properties contain a comma-separated list of
                    organization names to display when using the language with
                    two-character code <i>XX</i>. The list elements themselves
                    consist of a unique organization name (consistency is
                    required throughout the various configuration files, such as
                    the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    file), a colon, and the HTML display name. The example file
                    below configures Norwegian (bokmål) and English for one
                    imaginary organization.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.login.ticket_param</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the URL parameter containing the Moria ticket
                    ID.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to disallow SSO, if so chosen by
                    the user.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.ttl</code>
                    <p>
                    The time to live, in hours, for the cookie used to disallow
                    SSO.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to carry SSO ticket ID.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.ttl</code>
                    <p>
                    The time to live, in hours, for the cookie used to carry SSO
                    ticket ID.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.lang.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to store the user's preferred
                    language.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.login.default_language</code>
                    <p>
                    The default Moria language, which should match one of the 
                    two-letter language abbreviations already defined. The
                    example file below will use English.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.name</code>
                    <p>
                    The name of the cookie used to store a user's previously
                    selected organization.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.ttl</code>
                    <p>
                    The time to live, in hours, for the cookie used to store the 
                    user's previously selected organization.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.faqlink</code>
                    <p>
                    The URL to the FAQ document.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Demo Servlet Properties">
                <p>
                The following properties are exclusively used by the demo
                servlet, but are required nonetheless:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.attributeNamespaceURI</code>
                    <p>
                    Used to construct the QName for mapping "remote"
                    <code>Attribute</code> type to a local type. Although the
                    demo servlet is not "remote" as such, it accesses Moria
                    through SOAP just as any other Moria client application,
                    thus requiring this mapping.
                    <!--
                    TODO: Remove reference to login.feide.no and update DemoServlet.
                    -->
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.serviceEndpoint</code>
                    <p>
                    The service endpoint. The example file below assumes Moria
                    is deployed locally, and will use version 2.0 of the SOAP
                    interface.
                    </p> 
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.master.attributeRequest</code>
                    <p>
                    A comma-separated list of attributes requested by the master
                    (in the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    referred to as a "service") demo service. The example file
                    below will cause the demo servlet to request the attributes
                    <i>someAttribute</i> as well as the virtual (meaning it
                    doesn't exist physically in the actual user element)
                    attribute <i>tgt</i>, which is the ticket granting ticket.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.master.username</code>
                    <p>
                    The username used by the demo servlet to access Moria as a
                    master (in the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    referred to as a "service") client service. The application
                    server's user database must be configured accordingly.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.master.password</code>
                    <p>
                    The password used by the demo servlet to access Moria as a
                    master (in the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    referred to as a "service") client service. The application
                    server's user database must be configured accordingly.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.slave.attributeRequest</code>
                    <p>
                    A comma-separated list of attributes requested by the slave
                    (in the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    referred to as a subservice) demo service. The example file
                    below will cause the demo servlet to request the attribute
                    <i>anotherAttribute</i>.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.slave.username</code>
                    <p>
                    The username used by the demo servlet to access Moria as a
                    slave (in the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    referred to as a "subservice") client service. The
                    application server's user database must be configured
                    accordingly.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.demo.slave.password</code>
                    <p>
                    The password used by the demo servlet to access Moria as a
                    slave (in the
                    <a href="#Authorization Manager">Authorization Manager</a>
                    referred to as a "subservice") client service. The
                    application server's user database must be configured
                    accordingly.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Information Servlet Properties">
                <p>
                The following required properties are used by the information
                servlet:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.information.feideattribs_xml</code>
                    <p>
                    Gives the path and name of the file containing the actual
                    attribute descriptions. The XML file contains a root element
                    <i>AttributeFile</i> with one or more <i>Attribute</i> child
                    elements. Each <i>Attribute</i> element must contain the
                    child elements <i>Key</i> (which has a text child element
                    giving the physical attribute name), <i>ResourceBundle</i>
                    (which has a text child element providing the localized
                    description text for the attribute), <i>Relevance</i> (which
                    has a text child element that is either
                    <code>Mandatory</code> or <code>Optional</code>), and
                    <i>Link</i> (which has a text child element that gives the
                    URL of this attribute to a web page describing the
                    attribute).
                    </p> 
                    <p>
                    Example attribute description file:
                    </p>
                    <source>
&lt;?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

&lt;attributefile>

    &lt;attribute&gt; 
        &lt;key&gt;mail&lt;/key&gt;
        &lt;resourcebundle&gt;rb_mail&lt;/resourcebundle&gt;
        &lt;relevance&gt;Mandatory&lt;/relevance&gt;
        &lt;link&gt;http://www.feide.no/dokumenter/feide-schema-current.html#mail&lt;/link&gt;
    &lt;/attribute>&gt;

&lt;/attributefile>
                    </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.information.url_prefix</code>
                    <p>
                    Should give the URL used to access to the information
                    servlet.
                    </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Status Servlet Property">
            <p>
                The following property are used by the status servlet:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <code>no.feide.moria.web.backendstatus.status_xml</code>
                    <p>Gives the path and name of the file containing the information
                    about the test-users. The XML file contains a rootelement <i>Testuserlist</i>
                    with one or more <i>User</i> child elements. Each <i>User</i> element must
                    contain the child elements <i>Name</i> (which has a text child element
                    giving the name of a test-user) and <i>Password</i> (which has a text child
                    element giving the password of a test-user).
                    </p>
                    <p>Example of a status.xml file</p>
                    <source>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="yes"?&gt;

&lt;Testuserlist&gt;

   &lt;User&gt;
      &lt;Name&gt;test@test.no&lt;/Name&gt;
      &lt;Password&gt;test&lt;/Password&gt;
   &lt;/User&gt;

&lt;/Testuserlist&gt;
			</source>
			</li>
		</ul>
        </subsection>
            <p>     
            Example Web Module configuration file:
            </p>
            <source>
#
# Configuration properties for Moria itself:
#

# The URL of the login servlet.
no.feide.moria.web.login.url_prefix=http://localhost:8080/moria/Login

# The name of the parameter used to contain the redirect URL when logging out.
no.feide.moria.web.logout.url_param=redirUrl

# Abbreviations and display names for available languages.
no.feide.moria.web.lang_common=nb:Bokm&amp;aring;l,en:English

# Organization names when using the language EN.
no.feide.moria.web.org_en=my.org:My Organization

# Organization names when using the language NB.
no.feide.moria.web.org_nb=my.org:Min organisasjon

# Name of URL parameter containing the Moria ticket ID.
no.feide.moria.web.login.ticket_param=moriaID

# Name of cookie used to disallow SSO.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.name=MoriaDenySSOCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookie used to disallow SSO.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.denysso.ttl=1

# Name of cookie used to carry SSO ticket ID.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.name=MoriaSSOCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookie used to carry SSO ticket ID.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.sso.ttl=1

# Name of cookie used to store user's preferred language.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.lang.name=MoriaUserLanguageCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookies used to store user's preferred language.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.lang.ttl=1

# Default Moria language.
no.feide.moria.web.login.default_language=en

# Name of cookie used to store user's previously selected organization.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.name=MoriaUserOrganizationCookie

# Time to live, in hours, for cookies used to store user's previously selected organization.
no.feide.moria.web.cookie.org.ttl=1

# Link to the Moria2 FAQ.
no.feide.moria.web.faqlink=http://localhost:8080/moria/faq




#
# Configuration properties relevant for the demo service (DemoServlet):
#

# Used to construct the QName for mapping remote Attribute type to local type.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.attributeNamespaceURI=https://login.feide.no/moria/v2_0/Authentication

# The service endpoint.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.serviceEndpoint=http://localhost:8080/moria/v2_0/Authentication

# A comma-separated list of attributes requested by the main service.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.master.attributeRequest=someAttribute,tgt

# The username used by DemoServlet to access Moria as a main service.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.master.username=demo_service

# The password used by DemoServlet to access Moria as a main service.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.master.password=demo_service

# A comma-separated list of attributes requested by the subservice.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.slave.attributeRequest=anotherAttribute

# The username used to access Moria as a subservice.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.slave.username=demo_subsystem

# The password used to access Moria as a subservice.
no.feide.moria.web.demo.slave.password=demo_subsystem


#
# Configuration properties relevant for the information service (InformationServlet):
#

# Giving the URL to the information servlet.
no.feide.moria.web.information.url_prefix=http://localhost:8080/moria/Information

# Configuration property for the attribute description file name.
no.feide.moria.web.information.feideattribs_xml=/some/path/attribs.xml

#
# Configuration property relevant for the status service (StatusServlet):
#

# Configuration proprety for the status.xml file.
no.feide.moria.web.backendstatus.status_xml=/some/path/status.xml
            </source>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
