<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 UNINETT FAS

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option)
any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple
Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.

$Id$
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Design</title>
    <author email="lars.preben.arnesen@conduct.no">Lars Preben S. Arnesen</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Introduction">

      <p>FEIDE (Federated Electronic Identity for Education) is a project
    with the goal of establishing a common electronic identity for Norwegian
    academic users. The three main parts are</p>

      <ul>
        <li>
        user administration and defining inter-institutional role definitions
        </li>
        <li>
          common access control for Internet services with well defined
          authentication and authorization mechanisms
        </li>

        <li>
          secure electronic ID built on public key encryption
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        FEIDE consists of several sub-projects, one of them with the goal
        to create a HTTP based authentication service for web resource providers.
        This sub-project has been named <i>Moria</i>.
      </p>

      <p>
        In FEIDE each academic institution has its own user management system
        for their students and employees, but services at one institution should
        be able to allow access to a user from another institution without
        importing that user into its own user administration system. FEIDE
        requires access to an LDAP front end of the user administration system
        (Enterprise Directory System) to provide such service. Potentially more
        than hundred institutions with a total of a few hundred thousand users
        will be a part of FEIDE. The number of services that requires access to
        user data from FEIDE are expected to be in the hundreds, if not thousands.
        In this scenario FEIDE cannot trust every one of the FEIDE enabled
        services (services that receives user data from FEIDE). Without such trust
        FEIDE will not allow service providers to get access to the user's
        user-name and password, requiring the authentication to be done by FEIDE
        and not by the service itself.
      </p>

      <p>
        This paper describes the authentication model implemented by Moria.
        This model is based on the user being redirected to the FEIDE login system
        when the web resource requests authentication. The authentication consists
        of two steps:
        <ol>
          <li>
            Establishing an authentication session and redirect of user to
            the login page
          </li>

          <li>
            Web resource collects data about the user when s/he returns
            after being authenticated
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Interactive authentication">

      <p>Moria consists of two interfaces: a SOAP based interface for the
    client (web resource) and a html interface for the user.</p>

      <table>
        <tr><th>Name</th><th>Explanation</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Enterprise Directory Server</td>
          <td>LDAP (Lightweight Directory Access Protocol) server used by
            each institution/organization</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Moria</td>
          <td>FEIDE's Login Service</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Web resource</td>
          <td>The service (client) that requires authentication and user
            information</td>
        </tr>
      </table>

      <p>
        When a web resource requires user authentication, it requests an
        authentication session from Moria. The request contains two parameters: a
        list of requested attributes and a URL that the user will be redirected
        back to after successful authentication. (The URL will be supplied with a
        ticked for retrieval of the requested user attributes.) Moria will perform
        basic HTTP authentication of the client (web service) along with
        authorization. If the client is unknown to Moria, or a known client
        requests attributes that it&#39;s not authorized to see, the request will
        be denied. If Moria accepts the client&#39;s request, a URL to Moria&#39;s
        login page is returned to the client. The URL contains a ticked that
        connects the user to the created authentication session (Moria session)
        and client then sends a 302 redirect response to the users web browser,
        with the Location header set to be the URL returned from Moria.</p>

      <p>
        The user's browser now performs a GET request for Moria's
        login page. The supplied ticket (Moria session ID) is verified and if the
        session exists a login page is returned to the user. The login page
        contains the name of the resource and what kind of data it has requested
        about the user. The browser then sends a POST request with the users
        user-name and password, to Moria. Moria uses the index server, LIMS, to
        locate the LDAP server that contains the user data.</p>

      <p>
        Moria binds to the LDAP server, using the supplied user-name and
        password as credentials. The connection is stored in the Moria session and
        the user is redirected back to the web service that requested the
        authentication. The web resource (client) now receives a request from the
        user&#39;s browser, with the ticket. The client then requests user data
        from Moria by supplying the ticked in a SOAP request. Moria again performs
        client authentication and - given that the ticket is valid and the client
        is the same client that initiated the authentication - fetches user data
        from the LDAP server and returns it as a data set to the client. An empty
        data set indicates that the user is registered in the LDAP server, but no
        attributes are requested (or the requested attributes aren&#39;t available
        from the LDAP server). A user is never redirected back to the web resource
        if the authentication failed. It is not possible to request user data from
        a Moria session without an authenticated connection to the LDAP server.</p>

      <p>
        When Moria has delivered user data to the client, FEIDE&#39;s web
        authentication service is finished. It is now up to the client to store
        the data as long as it needs it. If the client needs more data, or the
        same data once more, from FEIDE, it has to initiate a new authentication
        loop.
      </p>

      <img src="interactive_auth.png"/>

      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>User requests a web resource (1)</strong><br/>
          The user requests a access restricted web resource, typically by
          a GET request from a web browser.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The web resource requests an authentication session
          from Moria(2,3)</strong><br/>
          A request for an authentication session is sent from the web
          resource service to Moria. Moria responds by returning a URL to the
          login page.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>The users browser is redirected to the FEIDE login
          page (4-6)</strong><br/>

          A redirect response is sent to the users browser, with the
          location header set to the URL that Moria returned. The browser then
          sends a GET request for the login page and the user is presented with
          a login form.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>User-name and password are transmitted to the login
          service (7)</strong><br/>

          The user submits a HTML form with his/her user-name and password
          to Moria.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>Authentication (8,9)</strong>

          Moria uses LIMS to find the correct LDAP server and opens a
          connection to it using the user's credentials. The LDAP connection
          is stored in the Moria session for later use. If the authentication
          failed the user is presented with a error message and a new login
          form.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>Redirect back to the web resource service (10,11)</strong>

          The user is redirected back to the web resource, with a ticked
          supplied in the URL. This ticket is generated after a successful
          authentication.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>Retrieval of the user attributes (12,13)</strong>

          The client requests the user attributes from Moria, identified
          by the ticket. If the ticket is valid and the client is the one that
          requested the authentication in the first place, Moria returns the
          requested user attributes - if any. If no user attributes are
          requested (or available) an empty data set is returned as a
          confirmation that the user is authenticated but no data is available.
        </li>

        <li>
          <strong>Access to the web resource(14)</strong>

          The web resource is returned to the user's client.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section name="Single Sign On">

      <p>
        Single Sign-On is a requested feature in Moria both from users and
        web service providers. Users don't want to supply their username and
        password every time they access a new web service and the service
        providers want to be able to authenticate the users to subsystems. The
        current version of Moira has SSO for users which means that users can roam
        between services without performing more than one interactive login. Even
        before Moria went in production developers started to demand proxy
        authentication functionality, mainly when developing portals that requires
        to authenticate to other components on behalf of the user.</p>


    <subsection name="Ticket based reauthentication (SSO Light)">

      <p>
        The ticked based reauthentication uses the existing Moria model. The
      first time a user logs into a service via Moria, a ticked is stored in a
      cookie. The next time the user is redirected to Moria for login Moria uses
      the ticket to find the authentication session from last login. If it still
      exist (i.e. the session has not timed out), the user is immediately
      redirected back to the web service and the web service get access to the
      cached user data. If reauthentication cannot be used, the user is
      presented with a login form and a regular authentication process is
      performed.</p>

      <p>There are three scenarios when ticked based reauthentication fails,
      and a normal authentication process is required:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          The ticket refers to a non-existing authentication session. This
          happens when the a session times out and thus is removed from the
          session store or if the session has been removed for any other reason.
        </li>

        <li>
          The web service requests user attributes that Moria does not
          allow to be cached. The attributes are not stored in the
          authentication session and have to be retrieved from the LDAP server,
          which requires the user to supply their username and password.
        </li>

        <li>
          The web service insists that the user performs a regular
          authentication. Before critical operations, typically writing data,
          some services want to reauthenticate the user to be sure that no
          impersonator issues commands as the user. When requesting a user
          authentication the web service can insist that SSO should not be used.
          In this case Moria will remove the cached authentication session and
          present the user with a login form.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Proxy authentication">

      <p>For both of the following examples the following amendments to
      standard authentication process apply:</p>

      <li><strong>Step 2</strong>
            The service asks Moria for an additional attribute during the
            initialization of the authentication process: a ticket granting
            ticket (TGT).
          </li>
          <li><strong>After step 9</strong>
            Moria generates the TGT.
          </li>
          <li><strong>Step 13</strong>
            TGT returned to service.
          </li>

      <p>Both scenarios describes SSO after a regular authentication process
      has been performed.</p>

     <img src="proxy_auth.png"/>

        <ol>
          <li>
            <p>Service 1 (S1) requests, from Moria, tickets to log into
            service 2 (S2). S1 supplies the TGT obtained from Moria in the
            regular user authentication process.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>Upon the request Moria looks up the session and associated
            user id (UID) using the TGT as session identificator. A new ticket
            is generated for S2 and returned to S1. This ticket can only be used
            once and only by S2.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>S1 relays the ticket to S2, probably with other parameters.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>S2 uses the ticket to fetch attributes from Moria. The request
            must contain both the ticked and a list of attributes. S2 can also
            ask for a TGT that it can use to log into other sub systems.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>Moria either returns the requested attributes or denies the
            request (due to timeout or if S2 has requested non-cached attributes
            or attributes it&#39;s not allowed to get access to)</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>If the authentication was successful, S2 probably returns the
            data S1 requested.</p>
          </li>
        </ol>


      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Other services">
      <B>TODO: directAuthentication</B>
      <br/><B>TODO: verifyUserExistence</B>
    </section>

    <section name="Moria internals">
      <p>
        <b>TODO: Intro, module based</b><br/>
        <img src="moria2.png"/>
      </p>

      <subsection name="Controller">
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Configuration">
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Authorization">
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Store">
        <b>TODO: Bjørn Ola</b>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Store">
        <b>TODO: Bjørn Ola</b>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Directory">
        <b>TODO: Cato</b>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Security">
      <p>All communication to and from Moria is encrypted by SSL. The LDAP
    servers and web resources are required to trust Moria's SSL server
    certificate, signed by VeriSign. FEIDE does not require encrypted
    communication between the user and the web resource, but it is strongly
    encouraged.</p>

      <p>Moria uses a memory resident authorization data structure for
    authorization of the client. Each client must use basic authentication
    when performing SOAP requests and the principal is used to look up
    authorization from the authorization data structure. Every client is
    associated with a set of attributes (the set is empty for anonymous
    authentications). Only this set, or a subset of it, can be requested by
    the client. Any attempt to request other attributes will result in an
    exception when the client requests an authentication session.</p>

      <p>The ticket (or Moria session ID) is changed after authentication to
    minimize the risk of hijacking, and is generated according to the IETF
    UUID draft specification to be practically impossible to guess. The only
    place to hijack a session is in step 10 and 11 (redirect back to web
    resource). A hijacker has to intercept and stop the request between Moria
    and user or between user and web resource. The hijacker then has to use
    the ticket to present it self to the web resource and continue as an
    authenticated user. If the connection is encrypted, this risk is reduced
    significantly. Remember that session hijacking can be done at any time
    after the authentication, by eavesdropping the communication between the
    user and web resource. The possibility for session hijacking is reduced to
    virtually zero if all communication between the user and web resource is
    encrypted - this includes the redirect from Moria back to the web
    resource.</p>

      <p>Moria uses two different timeouts for the Moria session. If the user
    does not supply user-name and password within a given number of seconds
    (typically a few minutes), the session is removed and the user has to go
    back to the web resource to start a new authentication loop. After the
    user has been authenticated and redirected back to the web resource, the
    Moria session is only active for a few seconds. If the client does not
    request the user data from Moria during this time, the session is removed
    and the LDAP connection closed. This renders the ticked invalid and a new
    authentication loop is required to get user attributes from Moria.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>