<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 UNINETT

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option)
any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple
Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.

$Id$
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>From Moria1 to Moria2</title>
		<author email="cato.olsen@uninett.no">Cato Olsen</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="From Moria1 to Moria2">
            <p>
                This chapter is primarily for service developers that have some
                experience with the previous generation of Moria (<b>Moria1</b>)
                and wish to migrate to Moria2.
            </p>
			<p>
                We will briefly describe the changes between the previous and
                current generations, and outline the steps necessary to migrate
                a Moria1-enabled service to Moria2.
			</p>

			<subsection name="Differences Between Moria1 and Moria2">
				<p>
                    The Moria2 v2.0 SOAP interface is a direct port of the
                    Moria1 v1.0 SOAP interface, which was never released. The
                    new features of Moria2 becomes evident in the v2.1
                    interface; therefore we will compare this with the Moria1
                    v0.9 SOAP interface.
                </p>
                <p>
                    There are basically three differences between the Moria1
                    v0.9 and the Moria2 v2.1 SOAP interface.
    				<ol>
    				    <li>
                            The <b>SOAP interface has been reworked</b>; proper
                            versioning of the interface has been added, the
                            methods have been renamed, and improved error
                            handling has been integrated into the SOAP
                            interface.
    				    </li>
    					<li>
                            Support for <b>direct, non-interactive authentication</b>;
                            services may collect user credentials themselves and
                            authenticate/retrieve user attributes without the
                            need for a HTTP redirect.
    					</li>
    					<li>
                            Support for <b>ticket based single sign-on</b>; a
                            service, on successfully authenticating a user, may
                            request a ticket granting ticket and generate proxy
                            tickets for other services. These so-called
                            subservices may then use the proxy tickets to
                            authenticate the user directly, as well as to
                            request user attributes.
    					</li>
    				</ol>
                </p>
			</subsection>
            
			<subsection name="Migrating From Moria1 to Moria2">
				<p>
                    For those accustomed to the Moria1 SOAP interface, the
                    migration to Moria2 is as simple as:
    				<ol>
    					<li>
                            Generating new client-side stubs with your SOAP
                            library of choice, based on the new WSDL.
    					</li>
    					<li>
                            Changing your code to match the similar, but renamed
                            methods (which will give stub methods with different
                            names than you might be used to).
    					</li>
    				</ol>
                    For those who have been using the pre-compiled Mellon
    				client-side API with Moria1 v0.9, as deployed by the
    				<a href="http://www.feide.no">FEIDE</a> project (included in
                    the <code>feide-mellon-api-prod-0.9.jar</code> file), or the
    				matching servlet filter (included in the
    				<code>feide-mellon-filter-prod-0.9.jar</code> file), it is
                    a simple matter of replacing your old versions with the new
                    <b>Mellon2</b> API and/or filter. The API and filter are
                    backwards-compatible with existing Moria1-integrated
                    services, as well as offering the new and extended Moria2
                    functionality.
				</p>
				<p>
                    However, keep in mind that the official, and only supported,
                    interface to Moria (all versions) is the SOAP interface
                    presented through the WSDL. All other client-side APIs or
                    modules are considered example code, to be used at your own
                    risk.
                </p>
			</subsection>
            
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
