<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 UNINETT

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option)
any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple
Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.

$Id$
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Logout</title>
		<author email="cato.olsen@uninett.no">Cato Olsen</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Logout">
			<p>
                Logging out from an existing Moria2 SSO session is simply done
                by browsing to the Moria2 instance's logout URL, for example by
                redirecting the user. This will accomplish two things:
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Any existing Moria2 SSO cookie will be removed from the
                        user's browser.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Any existing SSO session matching the cookie will be
                        removed from Moria2 memory.
                    </li>
                </ol>
			</p>
            <p>
                In addition, the logout service also takes an <b>URL parameter</b>.
                Following logout, the user will be redirected to the URL passed
                on in this parameter instead of being shown the default Moria2
                logout page. This allows a service to decide how to present the
                user with logouts. The name of the parameter is configurable
                at the discretion of the Moria2 administrator.
            </p>
            <p>
                A service may very well implement its own form of
                session management. Please note that the logout procedure
                described here <b>only applies to a SSO session as it exists
                internally in Moria2</b>. It is technically possible for a user
                to log out of Moria2 and still be logged into such a service, or
                vice versa.
            </p>
            
            <subsection name="Logouts in FEIDE">
                <p>
                    Please refer to <a href="howto_service_feide.html">this</a>
                    chapter for a link to the logout service as found in the
                    instance of Moria2 run by <a href="http://www.feide.no">FEIDE</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The name of the logout URL parameter in the FEIDE instance is
                    <code>redirect</code>; thus, you would add the following
                    substring on the end of the logout service's URL:
                </p>
                <p align="center">
                    <code>?redirect=http://some.other.server/some/other/page</code>
                </p>
            </subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
